Guide to the Wickham Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Brothers and sisters; Child care; Children; Courtship; Death; Education -- Vermont; Education, Secondary -- Vermont; Families; Indians of North America -- Missions; Marriage; Missionaries; Spouses of clergy; Stepmothers; Women teachers; Women; Colony (Okla.); Connecticut -- Social life and customs; Manchester (Vt.) -- History; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; Oxford (N.Y.) -- History; Southern States -- Description and travel; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Vermont -- Religious life and customs; Diaries; Photographs; Sermons; Clergy; Educators; Children -- Health and hygiene; Adriance, Isaac, 1794-1862; Agnew, John Holmes, 1804-1865; Anderson, James, 1798-1881; Bacon, Thomas Scott, 1825-1904; Bartlett, Charles, 1795-1859; Bascom, W. F.; Bates, Joshua, 1776-1854; Black, William P.; Bonney, Elijah Hayward, 1816-1882; Burnham, William A.; Carpenter, Amos, 1753-1832; Clark, A. G.; Clark, Mary Daggett Merwin, 1817-1892; Clayton, John M. (John Middleton), 1796-1856; Cochran, A. G.; Coleman, Lyman, 1796-1882; Dean, Velie H.; Delavan, George Edwin; Douglass, Thomas; Ellsworth, J. C.; Furniss, Henry B.; Gilbert, Simeon; Glen, William R.; Goodell, William, 1792-1867; Hall, Emily Baldwin Merwin, 1821-; Hall, Gordon, 1823-1879; Hamlin, Cyrus, 1811-1900; Hamlin, Mary E.; Harris, John; Hinsdale, Charles J. (Charles James), 1796-1871; Hitchcock, Sophia Porter, 1797-1841; Holmes, Isaac E. (Isaac Edward), 1796-1867; Hudson, Cyrus; Isham, Pierpoint; Kibbe, Simeon Terry, 1794-1825; Labaree, Benjamin, 1801-1883; Landon, Caroline Powell Roe, 1859-1897; Leonard, William B.; Loomis, Aretas; Ludlow, H. G. (Henry Gilbert), 1797-1867; Marvin, Clarina B. Merwin, 1815-1899; Mather, Sarah, 1779-; McBurney, W. A.; Merwin, Alexander Moss, 1839-1905; Merwin, Clarina Bradley Taylor, 1788-1859; Merwin, Samuel John Miles, 1819-1888; Merwin, Samuel, 1781-1856; Merwin, Timothy Taylor, 1807-1885; Newton, Ephraim H. (Ephraim Holland), 1787-1864; Page, Elizabeth Merwin Roe, 1861-1943; Parker, William H. (William Henry), 1809-1889; Plumb, Elijah W. (Elijah Whiton), 1798-1879; Porter Eleazar, 1806-1886; Porter, Theodore Woolsey, 1799-1855; Porter, Timothy Dwight, 1797-1880; Pratt, P. S.; Prentiss, George Lewis, 1816-1903; Roberts, E. P.; Roe, Alfred Cox, 1823-; Roe, Emma Wickham, 1832-1906; Roe, Joseph Wickham, 1871-; Roe, Mary Wickham, 1863-1941; Sanford, Ezekiel, 1796-1822; Schauffler, Margaret Reynolds, 1896-1994; Slade, William, 1786-1859; Smith, Reuben, 1767-; Smith, Thomas Mather, 1796-1864; Smith, Truman, 1791-1884; Snell, Moses Porter, 1839-1909; Stafford, Ward, 1788-1851; Stebbins, Esther Wickham, 1802-1854; Stebbins, George; Steele, Joseph, 1801-1872; Stone, Randolph, 1790-1843; Stowell, Abijah, 1815-1889; Taylor, Timothy, -1802; Tefft, I. K. (Israel Keech), 1794-1862; Thompson, N. LaRue P.; Torrey, E. M.; Warner, William; Wickham, Abigail, 1809-1872; Wickham, Daniel Hull, 1771-1853; Wickham, Daniel Hull, 1812-1893; E. M. W. (Elizabeth Merwin Wickham), 1810-1901; Wickham, Joseph D.; Wickham, Joseph D. (Joseph Dresser), 1797-1891; Wickham, Mary Dresser, 1776-1854; Wilcox, Philo Beckwith, 1818-1898; Wood, Susan Townsend Merwin, 1812-1898; Youle, Joseph, 1796-1820; Merwin family; Wickham family; Burr and Burton Seminary; Burr Seminary; Middlebury College -- History; Oxford Academy (Oxford, Chenango County, N.Y.); Presbyterian Education Society; Washington Institute (New York, N.Y.); Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1815; Rowe family; Porter family
- Correspondence, 1794-1901; Series I; 6.25 linear feet (14 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, fills Boxes 1-14 of the Wickham Family Papers and is chronologically arranged. Undated letters are divided by correspondent and are found in folders 383-395. Oversize correspondence is located in Box 14.
  - Correspondence, 1794-1822 May (Box 1, Folder 1-24)
  - Correspondence, 1822 June - 1834 October (Box 2, Folder 25-48)
  - Correspondence, 1834 November - 1839 March (Box 3, Folder 49-72)
  - Correspondence, 1839 April - 1841 October (Box 4, Folder 73-97)
  - Correspondence, 1841 November - 1845 September (Box 5, Folder 98-121)
  - Correspondence, 1845 October - 1849 June (Box 6, Folder 122-147)
  - Correspondence, 1849 July - 1852 August (Box 7, Folder 148-178)
  - Correspondence, 1852 September - 1856 July (Box 8, Folder 179-215)
  - Correspondence, 1856 August - 1863 (Box 9, Folder 216-267)
  - Correspondence, 1864 - 1886 November (Box 10, Folder 268-309)
  - Correspondence, 1886 December - 1893 August (Box 11, Folder 310-347)
  - Correspondence, 1893 September - 1901 (Box 12, Folder 348-382)
  - Roe, Emma Wickham to Elizabeth, Merwin Wickham, undated (Box 13, Folder 383)
  - Roe, Emma Wickham to Joseph Dresser Wickham and Elizabeth Merwin Wickham, undated (Box 13, Folder 384)
  - Wickham, Elizabeth Merwin to Emma Wickham Roe, undated (Box 13, Folder 385-386)
  - Wickham, Elizabeth Merwin to Joseph Dresser Wickham, undated (Box 13, Folder 387-388)
  - Wickham, Elizabeth Merwin to Susan Williams Roe, undated (Box 13, Folder 389)
  - Wickham, Elizabeth Merwin: letters to, undated (Box 13, Folder 390)
  - Wickham, Joseph Dresser to Elizabeth Merwin Wickham, undated (Box 13, Folder 391)
  - Wickham, Joseph Dresser to Emma Wickham Roe, undated (Box 13, Folder 392)
  - Wickham, Joseph Dresser: letters to, undated (Box 13, Folder 393)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 394)
  - Letter fragments, undated (Box 13, Folder 395)
  - Oversize
    - Correspondence, 1817-1818, 1832-1833, 1839 (Box 14, Folder 396-400)
- Family Papers, 1785-1958; Series II; 1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  FAMILY PAPERS, filling Boxes 15-18, is arranged alphabetically by person or subject and then chronologically.
  - Album, 1879 (Box 15, Folder 401)
  - Cooke family genealogy, undated (Box 15, Folder 402)
  - Depew, Chauncy M.: address, 1895 (Box 15, Folder 403)
  - [Dickson]: silhouette and watercolor, 1818, 1873 (Box 15, Folder 404)
  - Ladies Charitable Association of Manchester, undated (Box 15, Folder 405)
  - Matteawan Female Missionary Association, undated (Box 15, Folder 406)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 15, Folder 407)
  - Merwin family papers, 1827-1900, undated (Box 15, Folder 408)
  - Merwin family: reminiscences about by Mary A. Smith, 1894 (Box 15, Folder 409)
  - Merwin, Clarina Bradley Taylor: death, 1859 (Box 15, Folder 410)
  - Merwin, Samuel: notebooks, undated (Box 15, Folder 411)
  - Miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 15, Folder 412)
  - Newspaper clippings: miscellaneous, 1864-1896, undated (Box 15, Folder 413)
  - Newspaper clippings: missionary work, 1898-1903 (Box 15, Folder 414)
  - Obituaries, 1857-1902, undated (Box 15, Folder 415)
  - Poems, 1851-1881, undated (Box 15, Folder 416)
  - Porter family genealogy, 1812-1818 (Box 15, Folder 417)
  - Porter family papers, 1812-1818 (Box 15, Folder 418)
  - Schauffler, Mary Reynolds: memorial service and reminiscences by Elizabeth Merwin Wickham, 1895 (Box 15, Folder 419)
    General note
    See also: box 5, folder 119
    See also: William Goodell letter 1845 Jul 11
  - Taylor family papers, 1800-1815, undated (Box 15, Folder 420)
  - Taylor, Timothy: deeds, 1785-1797 (Box 15, Folder 421)
  - Taylor, Timothy and Taylor, Elizabeth: deeds, 1798-1819 (Box 15, Folder 422)
  - Wickham family genealogy, undated (Box 15, Folder 423-424)
  - Wickham family: newspaper clippings, 1853-1901 (Box 15, Folder 425)
  - Wickham family photographs, 1874-1887, undated (Box 15, Folder 426)
    See also: box 18
  - Wickham family pictures, 1876-1894, undated (Box 16, Folder 427)
  - Wickham, Abigail: pupil register, 1836-1837 (Box 16, Folder 428)
  - Wickham, Elizabeth Merwin
    - Bills and receipts, 1892-1898 (Box 16, Folder 429-433)
    - Cancelled checks, 1891-1894 (Box 16, Folder 434)
    - Compositions, 18227-1828 (Box 16, Folder 435)
    - Estate papers, 1901-1908 (Box 16, Folder 436)
    - Manchester, (Vermont) Journal articles, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 437)
    - Memberships, 1897-1900, undated (Box 16, Folder 438)
    - Obituaries written by, 1868-1898, undated (Box 16, Folder 439)
    - Oxford Academy, 1833-1834 (Box 16, Folder 440)
    - Oxford Academy reminiscence, 1894 (Box 16, Folder 441)
    - Papers, 1825-1901, undated (Box 16, Folder 442)
    - Poems, 1880-1897, undated (Box 16, Folder 443)
    - Reminiscences, 1891-1896 (Box 16, Folder 444)
  - Wickham, Joseph Dresser
    - Address on classical study, 1844 (Box 16, Folder 445)
    - Biographical sketch, 1891 (Box 16, Folder 446)
    - Burr Seminary, 1833-1900, undated (Box 16, Folder 447)
    - Cancelled checks, 1891 (Box 16, Folder 448)
    - Disputation on slavery, 1813 (Box 16, Folder 449)
    - Lock of hair, Gold and silver leaf, 1891, undated (Box 17, Folder 450)
    - List of occupants of room at Yale, 1893 (Box 17, Folder 451)
    - "A Long and Well-Spent Life", undated (Box 17, Folder 452)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1882-1958, undated (Box 17, Folder 453)
    - Papers, 1837-1887, undated (Box 17, Folder 454)
    - Poem to commemorate departure of missionaries to Hawaii, 1822 (Box 17, Folder 455)
    - Reminiscences, undated (Box 17, Folder 456)
    - Washington Institute, 1831, undated (Box 17, Folder 457)
  - Wickham, Mary Dresser
    - Death of, 1854 (Box 17, Folder 458)
    - Records of the Maternal Society of Spring Street Church, 1823-1826 (Box 17, Folder 459)
  - Wickham, William Hull, 1877, 1886, undated (Box 17, Folder 460)
  - Photograph album belonging to Elizabeth Merwin Wickham, 1827-1887, undated (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Joseph D. and Elizabeth (Merwin) Wickham, 1884 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Elizabeth Merwin Roe (later Mrs. Alfred Page), 1882 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mary Wickham Roe (later Mrs. Walter Roe), 1881 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mary Clark, 1878 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Emily B, Hall, 1883 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Dr. Gordon Hall, [1879?] (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - G. A. Hall, [1886?] (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mary Clark(Mrs. James (Hubbell?), 1888 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Rev. A. M. Merwin, 1885 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mrs. A. M. Merwin, 1885 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Gracie Merwin, May Merwin, Clara Hemenway, Charles Hemenway, Willie Mervin, 1884 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mrs. Mary J. Burnham, [1883?] (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Miss Mary A. Burnham, 1880 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - [Cyrus Hamlin], undated (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - W. A. Wickham, 1875 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Clara Merwin, 1887 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - May [Vermonta?] Peyser, [1886?] (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Geo. Wood Merwin, 1886 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mrs. Frederic Baker, 1887 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Frederic Baker, 1887 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - J. Edwards Porter, 1886 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Angelina K. Bender, undated (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Lulu Floyd Wickham, 1875 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - George Wickham, 1875 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Dr. Cox, undated (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - James Hadley, 1872 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Mrs. Lathrop, 1873 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - May Merwin, Gracie Merwin, 1878 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Prof. G. Boardman, 1880 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - May Merin, Grace Merwin, Willie Merwin, Clara Hemenway, Charles Hemenway, 1884 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Dr. Thomas L. [Coit], 1885 (Box 18, Folder 460)
    - Grover Cleveland, 1886 (Box 18, Folder 460)
- Diaries, 1813-1901; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Series III contains diaries kept by Joseph Dresser Wickham and Elizabeth Merwin Wickham. The diaries of Joseph Dresser Wickham fill folders 461-476 of Boxes 19-20. They are arranged in chronological order. The diaries of Elizabeth Merwin Wickham are in folders 477-490, while an unidentified diary is found in folder 491.
  - Wickham, Joseph Dresser
    - Journal, 1819 (Box 19, Folder 461)
    - Journals, 1821 (Box 19, Folder 462)
    - Sermon notes, 1821 (Box 19, Folder 463)
    - Journals, 1822 (Box 19, Folder 464)
    - Diaries, 1834-1837, 1868-1883 (Box 19, Folder 465-472)
    - Diaries, 1884-1891 (Box 20, Folder 473-476)
  - Wickham, Elizabeth Merwin
    - Diaries, 1866, 1868-1871, 1873-1881 (Box 20, Folder 477-481)
    - Diaries, 1882-1897 (Box 21, Folder 482-488)
    - Diaries, 1898-1901 (Box 22, Folder 489-490)
    - Diary, 1813-1819 (Box 22, Folder 491)
- Sermons, 1819-1890; Series IV; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Series IV consists of three boxes of chronologically arranged sermons written and delivered by Joseph Dresser Wickham. Undated sermons and sermon fragments follow dated sermons.
  - Sermons, 1819, 1822-1827, 1834-1836, 1843, 1846-1848 February (Box 23, Folder 492-508)
  - Sermons, 1848 Sep, 1850, 1854-1857, 1859-1865, 1867, 1869-1871 (Box 24, Folder 509-532)
  - Sermons, 1872, 1874, 1876, 1880-1882, 1890, undated (Box 25, Folder 533-550)
  - Sermon fragments, undated (Box 25, Folder 551)
- Printed Works, 1818-1901; Series V; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series V, PRINTED WORKS, fills Boxes 26-27 of the Wickham Family Papers. The material is arranged in a single alphabetical listing. The series concludes with two folders of memorabilia.
  - Almanacs, 1877-1887 (Box 26, Folder 552)
  - Bible owned by Elizabeth Merwin Wickham, 1872 (Box 26, Folder 553)
  - Books, 1818, 1830 (Box 26, Folder 554)
  - "The Child's Paper", 1876 (Box 26, Folder 555)
  - Colony Mission, 1900, undated (Box 26, Folder 556)
  - Essays, 1818-1887 (Box 26, Folder 557)
  - Historical Discourse United Church of New Haven, 1892 (Box 26, Folder 558)
  - A Long and Well-Spent Life, 1893 (Box 26, Folder 559-560)
  - A Long and Well-Spent Life, 1893 (Box 27, Folder 561)
  - A Lost Family Found, 1867 (Box 27, Folder 562)
  - Manchester, Vermont Congregational Church, 1871, 1879 (Box 27, Folder 563)
  - Memorials, 1879-1898 (Box 27, Folder 564)
  - Missions, 1889-1901 (Box 27, Folder 565)
  - The New Century for Women, 1876 (Box 27, Folder 566)
  - The Painter of "The Angellus, 1889 (Box 27, Folder 567)
  - Print of College Hill Poughkeepsie, undated (Box 28)
    See: MG Common Folio 47
  - Program, 1893 (Box 27, Folder 568)
  - Religious tracts, 1851, undated (Box 27, Folder 569)
  - Tour books, 1846-1890 (Box 27, Folder 570)
  - Memorabilia
    - Academic robe belonging to Joseph Dresser Wickham, 1890 (Box 27, Folder 571)
    - Calling cards, undated (Box 27, Folder 572)